hello I'm Kaue from Brazil and in this
video I'll be doing a walkthrough
through Solana's new
Javascript API, more specifically
in this video we'll be taking a deeper
look into Solana's
example-helloworld repository in Github
showing you how to correctly install the
node package
set up your local Solana cluster build
both your rust or c-based project
then run it, modify it to make your own
and finally wrap up on how to close
everything down
and in order to make that happen there
are some requirements that this
repository has
first of all you need node.js and npm on
the latest version
the docker suite for your corresponding
operational system
wget for downloads and the whole
rust suite so you can build your project
for further resources regarding this and
other to Solana based projects you might
have
please check out their documents at the
following link, their Github repos
which comes with other awesome examples
and you can also reach out to me on
discord
using my username, Solana also has a very
active discord
user base, you can find its link in the
official website
to it then, first of all i'm going to
fork the repo
so I can later make my code available
for you guys
so, let's clone it into our working
directory
so, it's all done, I'm going to open
this folder on VSCode so we can code
it away
right now it's a good time to start up
our docker
service since i'm using Mac OS and I'm
not
using the native Mac application
I just installed a virtual machine to
run docker
there is some extra steps I have to take
they are detailed
here, there's this extra
port forwarding command that I have to
do and
this is actually lacking one other
command that we need in order to make
this repo work
which is to part forward this
8900 as well so
yeah, it's pretty standard, I already have
the docker, docker-machine
and virtualbox installed, so i'm just
going to
start my docker-machine
and then, if we try to list docker right
now
it's still not fining or daemon
so, what we need to use is this eval
function
so it's exported to our environment and
right now if we do
docker ps, we can check that it's running
right now
we can proceed to the repo instructions
itself
install the Solana Javascript API
which is done by
npm, or through yarn
i'm choosing npm so let's run this
so after 12 seconds everything is
already installed
so we are ready to go to follow through
with this tutorial
so, first of all, we need to export this
environment variable here which is
telling us
all these Solana variables needed in
order to
load the correct configuration, so
we're going to update our docker image
done, so it's already up to date, we
already have the
latest Solana image, and right now we can
start our local test network
so yeah, it's running right now you can
check
if it's running or not by running this
which shows the logs on the foreground
and to exit this you just have to cancel
the runtime twice so in my case it's
ctrl c
okay so it's running all right you can
check this
it's actually up to date
with the official node, in the source
folder we can see two
different examples one is built on rust
and the other one is built on c
we're going to be building the program c
directory here if you want to do another
kind of program
all you have to do is make another
folder here and then change the name
here accordingly
but in our case let's just run
the standard example for the time being
so okay, our directory was correctly
built
as you can see it's tested and it's
passing and all we need to do right now
is npm run start
and yeah that's it! if you look at the
code itself
is actually getting the Solana
parameters that it's getting from the
SDK header file and then it's checking
for some inconsistencies that we
fortunately did not run into, and after
all
it's going to just greet
our address here - our transaction - one
time
and log a hello with the success message
so, that's basically what happened here
very simple program
and if we want to do the same for rust
it's just the same command
so it took a lot more time to compile
the rust program
but once we run the same command you can
see that
as expected in a blockchain, the program
count
is still running, you have to keep in
mind that you don't have
the whole flexibility of the rust or the
c program languages
not even their standard libraries
because
since we're using a blockchain
everything
running there must be deterministic and
that prevents us from
using random functions time-based and
clock-based
thread-based functions as well so here
you can see
what's listed on for rust but
the same principles can be applied for c
so if we go here
and we try to include some standard
libraries like
time.h
or typec for instance
the program is going to crash and you
can't also use
implicit functions such as the very
classic printf as it's going
to cause a build error because it's
not importing directly from your
compiler, it's using the Solana SDK
so this is one thing that you have to
keep in mind, but for the time being
what we are going to do here is just
little by little modify the hello
world typescript, which
after modifying we don't need to rebuild
the program, we just need to
run npm run start once again
in order to see it work, so one thing
that we can do
is just let's just say that we want to
say more hellos
so let's just make our sayHello
function
be a loop for instance and see what
happens
as you can see, it's sequentially saying
a lot of
hellos, and this we can see that it's
permanently
registered in our cluster but
in typescript, am I bound to the same
limitations that I mentioned
both for c and for rust? Let's check it out
so let's create a function called
delay which is time based and it's going
to
make our program wait and call it
insider little loop here
as you can see, it is waiting now let's
do the following:
let's count the amount of characters in
our greeted public
key that are uppercase and greet this
address
the corresponding amount of times so
allright
and as you can see here, I've counted
manually
it is 25 uppercase characters
here we could just put i+1 one to
make it more
easy to understand but as you can see
all the greetings have been
successfully done and yeah I hope you
liked the video
I hope you found it very instructive for
any other doubts
you can check out uh the solana-labs'
repos
you can reach out to them on Discord
they're
very competent people and the project's
really awesome
and yeah, I hope I see you guys in the
next video and
keep on coding!